Guide to the William Peterfield Trent Daniel Defoe Research Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Peterfield Trent Daniel Defoe Research Collection
1830-1962
1912-1950
GEN MSS 859
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
14.38
(21 boxes)
Notes, newspaper clippings, manuscripts, typescripts, and printed material related to William Peterfield Trent's unpublished biography and bibliography of Daniel Defoe; and correspondence, notes, and printed material related to William Clinton Hutchins's editorial work on Trent's manuscripts.
Trent, William P. (William Peterfield), 1862-1939
Hutchins, Henry Clinton, 1889-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Clinton Hutchins, 1962.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Peterfield Trent (1862-1939)
William Peterfield Trent was born in Richmond, Virginia on November 10, 1862. He received his M.A. from the University of Virginia in 1884 and his LL.B from Wake Forest College in 1889. He joined the faculty of Sewanee, The University of the South as a professor of English in 1888. While there, he founded and edited The Sewanee Review (1892), founded the Sewanee Historical Society, and published several works, including the Life of William Gilmore Simms (1892).
In 1900 he moved to Columbia University as a professor of English and taught there until his retirement in 1929. His works include A History of American Literature, 1607-1865 (1903); Longfellow and Other Essays (1910); and Defoe--How to Know Him (1916). He was co-editor of the Columbia University edition of the complete works of John Milton (1931), and of the Cambridge History of American Literature (1917-1921). He also contributed articles on Defoe and other eighteenth-century authors to the Cambridge History of English Literature (1932).
For over fifteen years, Trent worked on a multi-volume bibliography of Daniel Defoe, as well as an accompanying biography. These works were never completed or published, although Yale Professor of English and Defoe scholar Henry Clinton Hutchins (1889-1962) carried out additional editorial work on Trent's materials during the 1930s and 1940s.
Trent married Alice Lyman in 1896, and the couple had two children, Lucia Trent Chaney and William P. Trent, Jr. He died, after several years of poor health, at home in Hopewell Junction, New York on December 7, 1939.
Scope and Contents
Notes, newspaper clippings, manuscripts, typescripts, and printed material related to William Peterfield Trent's unpublished biography and bibliography of Daniel Defoe; and correspondence, notes, and printed material related to Henry Clinton Hutchins's editorial work on Trent's manuscripts.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: I. William Peterfield Trent Research Materials, 1912-1939; II. Henry Clinton Hutchins Research Materials, 1830-1962.
Bibliographers -- United States; Biographers -- United States; English literature -- 18th century -- Bibliography; Defoe, Daniel, 1661?-1731; Defoe, Daniel, 1661?-1731 -- Bibliography; Trent, William P. (William Peterfield), 1862-1939
- I. William Peterfield Trent Research Materials, 1906-1934; 11.88; (19 boxes)
  Arrangement
  This material is not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  This group consists almost entirely of bundles and groups of notes by William Peterfield Trent for his planned bibliography and biography of Daniel Defoe. Folder titles have been transcribed when they appear.
  - "Notes on Defoe's Review " and " Notes on Political State ", undated (Box 1)
  - "Notes" and "Appendices to Chapter II", undated (Box 2)
  - "Contemporary things that may be worth examining", 1912-1930, undated (Box 3)
  - Notebooks, notepads and index cards, many containing information on dates in Defoe's life and publishing history, undated (Box 4)
  - Copies of title pages to French editions of Robinson Crusoe, undated (Box 5)
  - Research materials, including "Plausible, Dubious and Erroneous Attributions", 1912, undated (Box 6)
  - "Defoe's contemporaries--alphabetical", 1912-1930, undated (Box 7)
  - Research materials and newspaper clippings, 1912-1934, undated (Box 8)
  - Research materials, including some on Defoe's periodical publications, undated (Box 9)
  - Research materials and newspaper clippings, 1912, undated (Box 10)
  - Research materials and newspaper clippings, 1906-1912, undated (Box 11)
  - Research materials and newspapers clippings, 1912, undated (Box 12)
  - Lists of Defoe's publications and other research materials, undated (Box 13)
  - Catalog cards of Yale University's Defoe holdings, undated (Box 14)
  - Defoe biography, manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 15)
  - Defoe biography, manuscripts and typescripts; Defoe bibliography, manuscripts, undated (Box 16)
  - Defoe bibliography, manuscripts, undated (Box 17)
  - Defoe bibliography, typescripts, undated (Box 18)
  - Defoe bibliography, manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 19)
- II. Henry Clinton Hutchins Research Materials, 1830-1962; 2.5; (2 boxes)
  Correspondence, notes, manuscripts, and printed material related to Hutchins's scholarly work on Daniel Defoe, and particularly to his work with Trent's unpublished biography and bibliography.
  - Correspondence, notes, and research files on Defoe, 1910-1962, undated (Box 20)
    Includes correspondence with booksellers, academic and public libraries, and scholarly journals. One folder of correspondence, labeled "Personal," contains letters from relatives.
  - Research files on Defoe and printed material, 1830-1962, undated (Box 21)
    Contents include Walter Wilson, Memoirs of the Life and Times of Daniel De Foe (London, 1830) and William Lee, Daniel Defoe, His Life and Recently Discovered Writings (London, 1869).